Guide to the Basil Lee Whitener Papers, 1889-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Office Files Series, 1951-1968,primarily 1962-1968
  - Military and Veterans
    This file generally consists of correspondence between Whitener and his constituents concerning such matters as requests for transfers and reassignments, allotments, hardship discharges, efforts to locate a soldier, hospitalization benefits, disability claims, and appeals to the Board of Veterans Appeals. Usually, all correspondence for persons whose last name begins with the same letter of the alphabet has been kept together under that letter. Since these papers are very routine, concerning individual benefits and requests, rather than being topical in nature, only a representative sample has been retained. The letter C, a large letter which includes a wide range of ethnic groups, was chosen for retention.
    - C File:
      - Papers, 1964, Nov.-1965, Dec. (Box 265, Folder 10)
      - Papers,1966 (Box 266, Folder 1-2)
    - Military, General, 1965-1966 (Box 266, Folder 3)
      This folder primarily concerns the U.S. Army Reserve and the Army National Guard.
    - Veterans, General,1965 (Box 266, Folder 4)
  - School Letters,1968 (Box 266, Folder 5-6)
    Lists of names and addresses of members of the1968graduating classes for various North Carolina high schools which Whitener requested by letter.
  - Volumes:
    - Civil Rights, 1963-1964 (Box 266, Folder 7)
    - Government of the District of Columbia: A Long Term Financial Program for D. C., 1963 (Box 266, Folder 8)
    - Poor Folks at Home, 1966 (Box 267, Folder 1)
    - Proposal for a Demonstration Model of a Controlled High-Speed Superail Transit System for Mass Transportation: Washington, D. C. to Dulles International Airport, 1962 (Box 267, Folder 2)
    - Rail Rapid Transit for the Nation's Capital, 1965 (Box 267, Folder 3)
    - Report of City Council Public Hearings on the Rebuilding and Recovery of Washington, D. C. from the Civil Disturbances of April, 1968, 1968 (Box 267, Folder 4)
    - Report on Civil Disturbances in Washington, D. C., 1968 (Box 267, Folder 5)
  - Voter Lists,1957
    Lists include name, address, and political party affiliation.
    - Cleveland County:
      - Bethware-Dover Mill Precincts (Box 267, Folder 6-12)
      - Earl-West Kings Mountain Precincts (Box 268, Folder 1-20)
    - Gaston County:
      - Precincts No. 1-11 (Box 269, Folder 1-11)
      - Baker's-High Shoals Precincts (Box 270, Folder 1-13)
      - Kisers-Union Precincts (Box 271, Folder 1-9)
    - Gaston County Precincts, undated
      Four computer-produced lists of names of voters in Gaston County, including their addresses and political party affiliations. The names are grouped by precinct numbers (1-44), which are keyed to a list of precincts at the front of each folder. This list also includes the names of the townships in which the precincts are located.
      - Precinct Numbers:
        - 1-9 (City Hall-Grier Precincts) (Box 271, Folder 10)
        - 10-22 (Central-Belmont # 3 Precincts) (Box 271, Folder 11)
        - 23-33 (Catawba Heights-Cherryville # 2 Precincts) (Box 271, Folder 12)
        - 34-44 (Cherryville # 3-Stanley Precincts) (Box 271, Folder 13)
    - McDowell County
      - Crooked Creek-Old Fort # 1 Precincts (Box 272, Folder 1-6)
    - Rutherford County:
      - Alexander-Henrietta Precincts (Box 272, Folder 7-27)
      - Logan's Store-Union Precincts (Box 273, Folder 1-14)
- Office Information Series, 1956-1968
  Information on various topics that seems to have been needed for frequent use by Whitener's office staff. The following groups of material were discarded: lists of names and addresses to which autographed photographs of Whitener were mailed, samples of printed Christmas cards and calendars, information concerning office equipment such as typewriters, and receipts for purchases of office supplies.
  - Agriculture, 1963-1967 (Box 274, Folder 1)
  - Agriculture Yearbook, 1962-1967 (Box 274, Folder 2)
  - Catawba Valley Hosiery Club, 1965Concerning a speech Whitener made. (Box 274, Folder 3)
  - Census, 1966-1967Printed and mimeographed material published by the U.S. department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census. (Box 274, Folder 4)
  - Citizens, Naturalized, 1962-1963 (Box 274, Folder 5)
  - Civil Service, 1965-1967 (Box 274, Folder 6)
  - Congressional Record, 1963-1968 (Box 274, Folder 7)
  - Economic Development Act, 1965-1966Printed material produced by the U.S. Department of Commerce, Economic Development Administration. (Box 274, Folder 8)
  - Federal Employment Applications, 1968 (Box 274, Folder 9)
  - Lists, 1956-1967and undated (Box 275, Folder 1-8)
    This is the largest section of the series and contains various lists, rosters, and directories, which note the names and addresses of such North Carolina organizations as the Licensed General Contractors, members of the Young Democratic Clubs and the Medical Society of the State of North Carolina, etc. There is some correspondence, consisting mostly of requests for lists.
  - National Defense Education Act, 1958-1966and undatedPrinted and mimeographed information concerning student loans, graduate fellowships, teacher exchange opportunities, etc. (Box 276, Folder 1)
  - National Foundation on the Arts and the Humanities, 1965-1966 (Box 276, Folder 2)
  - National Park Service, 1964-1967Printed material of the U.S. Department of the Interior, National Park Service. (Box 276, Folder 3)
  - Newcomers,1968 Letters Whitener wrote to new residents in his district. (Box 276, Folder 4)
  - Political, 1959-1967Campaign material for various candidates. Oversize in Box 307. (Box 276, Folder 5)
  - Political, Broyhill, 1966-1968- James Broyhill was the Congressional Representative for the 9th District, North Carolina. The folder consists of Broyhill campaign material and a few other campaign letterheads. (Box 276, Folder 6)
  - Political Fund Raising, 1965and undated (Box 276, Folder 7)
  - Press Releases,1963, 1967and undated (Box 276, Folder 8)
  - Questionnaire,1963 (Box 276, Folder 9)
  - Questionnaire,1965 (Box 276, Folder 10)
  - Questionnaire,1968 (Box 276, Folder 11)
  - Selective Service,1967 (Box 276, Folder 12)
  - TACT Committee of Shelby (N.C.), 1962-1964and undated (Box 277, Folder 1)
  - Telephone Account, 1957-1968Long distance service records giving calls placed, by whom, to whom, date, etc. (Box 277, Folder 2-4)
  - Trade Mission, 1963-1965Mimeographed and printed material (Box 277, Folder 5)
- Personal Series, 1889-1968and undated,primarily 1957-1968
  Included are papers relating more directly to Whitener's private and unofficial affairs. The matters contained here range from such things as Whitener's admission to the District of Columbia Bar and his weekly radio program, to Whitener's apartment rental, bills and receipts, and family reunions.
  These files were in disarray, and therefore have been organized into three major categories: Congresses, Subject Files, and General Files. In the first subdivision, Congresses, the papers are grouped by Congress, session, and then alphabetically within each session of Congress. This information was evidently kept together in this manner by Whitener's office. There is repetition in some categories in various Congresses, such as Correspondence (Alphabetical). The explanatory notes for such categories have been included in the inventory only with the earliest Congress in which the category appears. The category, Congresses, forms the bulk of the Personal Series.
  In the Subject Files are topics such as the National Federation of Independent Business, which span several years. The General Files contain biographical information, financial papers, miscellany, clippings, printed material, and pictures.
  The following types of items were discarded from the Personal Series:
  1. Routine bills, receipts, and statements pertaining to the ordering of office supplies from the U.S. House of Representatives Stationery Room.
  2. Many bills, receipts, and other personal financial papers.
  3. Routine items from the voluminous "General" files. The remaining items were filed among various appropriate categories, such as correspondence, printed material, and finanical papers.
  4. Certain medical records.
  - Congresses
    - 85th Congress, 1st Session, 1957
      - The Coronet Rental,1957 (Box 278, Folder 1)
        Concerns the rental arrangements for Whitener's Washington, D. C, apartment.
      - Correspondence (Alphabetical), 1956-1957
        Letters are arranged alphabetically by the last name of correspondents. This file is representive of the Correspondence (Alphabetical) categories that are listed for subsequent congresses. Typical items are congratulations on various honors, expressions of sympathy upon deaths of family members, thank you letters, and invitations. Some of the correspondence is signed by Herbert Lineberger, secretary and later administrative assistant to Congressman Whitener. The1956letters that occur in this section were invitations, written in December, to a reception Whitener held in January,1957.
        - A-H (Box 278, Folder 2-9)
        - I-V (Box 279, Folder 1-15)
        - W-Z (Box 280, Folder 1-2)
      - Correspondence (Financial),1957 (Box 280, Folder 3)
        Letters pertaining to requests for contributions to charitable and political organizations, dues, life insurance premiums, etc. This file is representive of the items found in Correspondence (Financial) categories that are listed for subsequent congresses.
      - Correspondence (General), 1956-1957 (Box 280, Folder 4)
        Consists of letters culled from a file entitled General Papers, and contains items similiar in nature to the Correspondence (Alphabetical). Whitener's office kept this general material in strict chronological order, rather than in alphabetical order by last name of correspondent. This file is typical in nature of the Correspondence (General) categories that are listed for subsequent congresses, and contains congratulations, references to Whitener's social security standing and military duty, mention of the inauguration, etc.
      - Financial Papers, 1956-1957 (Box 280, Folder 5)
        A large percentage of these items were discarded because they consisted of routine, personal bills and receipts.
      - Inauguration of North Carolina Governor,1957 (Box 280, Folder 6)
      - Judiciary Committee, 1957 (Box 280, Folder 7)
        Correspondence between Whitener and various members of Congress in which Whitener requested support in being appointed to the Judiciary Committee. Earl Chudoff won an election as judge in Pennsylvania; his departure from Congress left a vacancy on the Judiciary Committee.
      - Radio: House Recording Studios,1957 statements, receipts, and invoices. (Box 280, Folder 8)
      - Radio and Television, 1957 (Box 280, Folder 9)
        Concerns Whitener's weekly radio broadcasts, including correspondence, news releases, memoranda, and a list of radio tapes made.
      - Recommendations,1957 (Box 280, Folder 10)
      - Retirement, 1957 (Box 280, Folder 11)
    - 85th Congress, 2nd Session, 1958
      - Caribbean Trip, 1958 (Box 280, Folder 12)
      - The Coronet Rental, 1958 (Box 280, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence (Alphabetical),1958
        - A-C (Box 280, Folder 14-16)
        - D-Z (Box 281, Folder 1-16)
      - Correspondence (Financial),1958 (Box 282, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence (General),1958and undated (Box 282, Folder 2)
      - Eleventh Congressional District of North Carolina Democratic Rally, 1958 (Box 282, Folder 3)
      - Financial Papers,1958 (Box 282, Folder 4)
      - Judiciary Committee, 1958Concerns Whitener's election to this Committee on Jan. 16, 1958. (Box 282, Folder 5)
      - Memoranda,1958 (Box 282, Folder 6)
        Numbered memoranda, dated Aug.-Dec., to Whitener from Herbert Lineberger at the Washington office detailing activities at the office.
      - Political,1958 (Box 282, Folder 7)
        Material relating to Whitener's notice of candidacy for the Democratic nomination in the1958primary for the office of Representative in Congress from the 11th Congressional District.
      - Radio: House Recording Studios, 1958 (Box 282, Folder 8)
      - Radio and Television, 1958and undated (Box 282, Folder 9-10)
        Contains such items as press releases concerning the topics of Whitener's weekly radio programs, schedules of when programs were to be aired, and some information about pay TV.
      - Recommendations,1958 (Box 282, Folder 11)
    - 86th Congress, 1st Session, 1959
      - Apartment Rental, 1959 (Box 282, Folder 12)
      - Circuit Court, 1959 (Box 282, Folder 13)
        Pertains to Whitener's admission to the bar of the Circuit Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia.
      - Congressional Record Insertions,1959 (Box 282, Folder 14)
      - Correspondence (Alphabetical),1959
        - A-Q (Box 282, Folder 283, Folder 1-18)
        - R-Z (Box 282, Folder 284, Folder 1-7)
      - Correspondence (Financial),1959 (Box 282, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence (General),1959and undated (Box 282, Folder 9)
      - District of Columbia Bar, 1959Concerns Whitener's admission to the bar. (Box 282, Folder 10)
      - Financial Papers,1959 (Box 282, Folder 11)
      - News Releases, 1959 (Box 282, Folder 12)
      - Paroles, 1959 (Box 282, Folder 13)
      - Radio Stations, 1959and undatedPrimarily information concerning Whitener's weekly Washington Report program on radio. (Box 282, Folder 14)
      - Radio: House Recording Studios, 1959 (Box 282, Folder 15)
      - Recommendation,1959 (Box 282, Folder 16)
      - Television, 1959 (Box 282, Folder 17)
    - 86th Congress, 2nd Session, 1960
      - Cherryville High School Band, 1959-1960 (Box 282, Folder 18)
        Contains letters in reference to the appearance of the band at the Cherry Blossom Festival in1960.
      - Congressional Record Insertions,1960 (Box 284, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence (Alphabetical),1960
        - A (Box 284, Folder 20)
        - B-Z (Box 285, Folder 1-24)
      - Correspondence (Financial),1960 (Box 285, Folder 25)
      - Correspondence (General)
        - Papers, 1960, Jan.-July (Box 285, Folder 26)
        - Papers, 1960, Aug.-Dec. (Box 286, Folder 1)
      - Financial Papers,1960 (Box 286, Folder 2)
      - Inauguration of North Carolina Governor (1961),1960 (Box 286, Folder 3)
      - News Releases,1960 (Box 286, Folder 4)
      - Paroles, 1960 (Box 286, Folder 5)
      - Radio: House Recording Studios, 1960 (Box 286, Folder 6)
      - Radio Station, 1960and undated (Box 286, Folder 7)
      - Recommendations,1960 (Box 286, Folder 8)
    - 87th Congress, 1st Session, 1961
      - Akers Meeting,1961 (Box 286, Folder 9-10)
        This meeting was an annual stag dinner given by John Akers, Robert Wren, and Whitener, which various Congressmen, state representatives, and businessmen attended.
      - Congressional Record Insertions,1961Copies of remarks by Whitener. (Box 286, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence (Alphabetical),1961
        - A-G (Box 286, Folder 12-18)
        - H-Z (Box 287, Folder 1-18)
      - Correspondence (Financial),1961 (Box 287, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence (General),1961 (Box 287, Folder 20)
      - European Trip (1961), 1961-1962 (Box 287, Folder 21)
      - Financial Papers,1961 (Box 287, Folder 22)
      - News Releases,1961Includes some telegrams. (Box 287, Folder 23)
      - Radio: Home Recording Studios, 1961 (Box 288, Folder 1)
      - Radio Stations,1961 (Box 288, Folder 2)
    - 87th Congress, 2nd Session, 1962
      - Congressional Record Insertions,1962 (Box 288, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence (Alphabetical),1962 (Box 288, Folder 4-26)
      - Correspondence (Financial),1962 (Box 288, Folder 27)
      - Correspondence (General),1962 (Box 289, Folder 1)
      - Democratic Registration,1962 (Box 289, Folder 2)
      - Financial Papers,1962 (Box 289, Folder 3)
      - News Releases,1962and undated (Box 289, Folder 4)
      - Political,1962and undated (Box 289, Folder 5)
      - Radio: House Recording Studios,1962 (Box 289, Folder 6)
      - Radio Program,1962 (Box 289, Folder 7)
      - Re-election, 1962 (Box 289, Folder 8)
        Included are candidacy forms to file for re-election, notice of candidacy, and certificate of nomination.
    - 88th Congress, 1st Session,1963
      - Congressional Record Insertions,1963 (Box 289, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence (Alphabetical)
        - A-G (Box 289, Folder 10-16)
        - H-Z (Box 290, Folder 1-16)
      - Correspondence (Financial),1963 (Box 290, Folder 17)
      - Correspondence (General),1963 (Box 290, Folder 18)
      - Financial Papers,1963 (Box 290, Folder 19)
      - News Releases,1963 (Box 290, Folder 20)
      - Radio: House Recording Studios,1963 (Box 291, Folder 1)
      - Radio Stations,1963and undated (Box 291, Folder 2)
      - Textile Exposition (1963), 1961-1963The exposition was evidently held in Bremen, Germany, during the week of September 22, 1963. (Box 291, Folder 3)
      - Travel, 1963 (Box 291, Folder 4)
      - Twenty-fifth International Space and Air Show, 1963This exhibition occurred in Paris from June 7-16, 1963. (Box 291, Folder 5)
      - Virginia Episcopal School Visit,1963 (Box 291, Folder 6)
    - 88th Congress, 2nd Session, 1964
      - Congressional Record Insertions,1964 (Box 291, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence (Alphabetical),1964
        - A-N (Box 291, Folder 8-22)
        - P-Z (Box 292, Folder 1-7)
      - Correspondence (Financial),1964 (Box 292, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence (General),1964 (Box 292, Folder 9)
      - Election Returns (1964), 1963-1964 (Box 292, Folder 10)
      - Far East Trip (1964), 1964-1965 (Box 292, Folder 11)
      - Financial Papers,1964 (Box 292, Folder 12)
      - News Releases,1964 (Box 292, Folder 13)
      - Radio: House Recording Studios,1964 (Box 292, Folder 14)
      - Radio Program,1964 (Box 292, Folder 15)
      - Stock Certificates for Harriet Whitener, 1964 (Box 292, Folder 16)
      - Sugg, Woodrow, 1964 (Box 292, Folder 17)
        Concerns an educational seminar for representatives of colleges in western North Carolina and public school officials from several counties.
    - 89th Congress, 1st Session, 1965
      - Bills introduced by Whitener, 1965 (Box 293, Folder 1)
      - Congressional Record Insertions,1965 (Box 293, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence (Alphabetical),1965 (Box 293, Folder 3-17)
      - Correspondence (Financial),1965 (Box 293, Folder 18)
      - Correspondence (General),1965 (Box 293, Folder 19)
      - Financial Papers,1965 (Box 293, Folder 20)
      - Inauguration of North Carolina Governor (1965), 1964-1965 (Box 293, Folder 21)
      - Inauguration of the President (1965), 1964-1965 (Box 293, Folder 22)
      - Meeting of Members of the North Carolina Business Executives Trade Study Mission, 1965 (Box 293, Folder 23)
        Concerns a reception and dinner, given by Whitener and Mr. and Mrs. Robert Wren for the members of the North Carolina Business Excutives Trade Study Mission and their wives.
      - News Releases,1965 (Box 293, Folder 24)
      - Radio: House Recording Studios,1965 (Box 294, Folder 1)
      - Radio Program,1965 (Box 294, Folder 2)
    - 89th Congress, 2nd Session, 1966
      - Campaign,1966North Carolina Congressional Campaign material. (Box 294, Folder 3)
      - Congressional Record Insertions,1966 (Box 294, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence (Financial),1966 (Box 294, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence (General),1966and undated (Box 294, Folder 6-7)
      - Financial Papers,1966 (Box 294, Folder 8)
      - Letters from Congressmen,1966 (Box 294, Folder 9)
        Correspondence to John O. Brock in Shelby, N.C., written on behalf of Whitener and containing impressions of his service in Congress.
      - Letters of Appreciation,1966 (Box 294, Folder 10)
        Primarily copies of letters of appreciation to Whitener from various persons. Both of the above folders of letters relate to a newspaper, Sentinel, that Brock planned to publish about Whitener's life.
      - News Releases,1966and undated (Box 294, Folder 11)
      - Political,1966 (Box 295, Folder 1)
        Primarily clippings concerning the North Carolina campaign for the Representative to Congress from the 10th District, including primary vote returns.
      - Radio: House Recording Studios,1966 (Box 295, Folder 2)
      - Radio Program,1966 (Box 295, Folder 3)
      - Tenth Congressional District Democratic Rally,1966It was held in Hickory, N.C., on October 31, 1966. (Box 295, Folder 4)
    - 90th Congress, 1st Session, 1967
      - Broyhill, James T., 1967 (Box 295, Folder 5)
        Included are remarks by Broyhill in the Congressional Record and copies of his Washington Report.
      - Congressional Record Insertions,1967 (Box 295, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence (Financial),1967 (Box 295, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence (General),1967 (Box 295, Folder 8-9)
      - Dominican Republic Trip (1967), 1966-1967 (Box 295, Folder 10)
      - Financial Papers,1967 (Box 295, Folder 11)
      - News Releases,1967 (Box 296, Folder 1)
      - Radio: House Recording Studios,1967 (Box 296, Folder 2)
      - Radio Program,1967Includes news releases. (Box 296, Folder 3)
    - 90th Congress, 2nd Session, 1968
      - Broyhill, James T., 1968 (Box 296, Folder 4)
      - Campaign,1968Pertains to the North Carolina Congressional campaign. (Box 296, Folder 5)
      - Campaign Advertising, 1968 (Box 296, Folder 6)
      - Congressional Record Insertions,1968 (Box 296, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence (Financial),1968 (Box 296, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence (General),1968 (Box 296, Folder 9)
      - Financial Papers,1968 (Box 297, Folder 1)
      - Invitations,1968 (Box 297, Folder 2-4)
      - News Releases,1968and undatedIncluded also are some copies of Congressman Whitener Reports to You. (Box 297, Folder 5-6)
      - Radio: House Recording Studios,1968 (Box 297, Folder 7)
      - Radio Program,1968 (Box 297, Folder 8)
        Included are draft questions for an interview and background information on the Tenth Congressional District of North Carolina.
      - Resume of 90th Congress, 2nd Session, 1968 (Box 297, Folder 9)
      - Speech to the North Carolina State Democratic Convention, 1968 (Box 297, Folder 10)
  - Subject Files
    - Address Labels, undated (Box 298, Folder 1)
    - Air Force Reserve, 1957-1965and undated (Box 298, Folder 2-7)
      Primarily contains papers relating to Whitener's status as a major in the U.S. Air Force Reserve and to his two-week Active Duty for training tours, such as the one in 1964 in Taipei, Taiwan.
    - Moore, Dan Killian, 1956and1964 (Box 298, Folder 8)
      Included are clippings concerning elections and primaries. Oversize items have been placed in Box 307.
    - National Federation of Independent Business, 1962-1966
      Survey of attitudes toward various topics, such as the national debt, the Common Market, labor unions, etc.
      - Correspondence, 1962-1966 (Box 298, Folder 9)
      - Ballots, Nos. 341-309 (Box 299, Folder 1-3)
    - Office Rent in Gastonia, 1957-1968 (Box 299, Folder 4)
    - Paroles, 1960-1965 (Box 299, Folder 5)
    - Political: Names and Addresses, undatedNames and addresses of companies and individuals. (Box 299, Folder 6)
    - Political: Precinct returns, undated (Box 299, Folder 7)
    - Reunions, 1957-1963Material for the Barrett and Whitener families. Laura Lee Barrett was Basil Whitener's mother. (Box 300, Folder 1)
    - Speech Material,1889, 1949-1960and undated (Box 300, Folder 2-4)
      Included are such items as clippings and excerpts from the Congressional Record. The 1889 items are Xerox copies of material pertaining to Rutherford College in Burke County, North Carolina.
    - United Nations, 1951-1956 (Box 300, Folder 5)